<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ilya Zakharau's Blog</title><link>https://izakharau.me/</link><description>Essays about APIs, No-code, and Product Management in the Enterprises</description><atom:link href="https://izakharau.me/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:ilya.zakharau@gmail.com"&gt;Ilya Zakharau&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License BY-NC-SA"
style="border-width:0; margin-bottom:12px;"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 13:56:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>API Design Tooling</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/api-design-tooling/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/api-design-tooling/back.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article is a part of the &lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/pages/api-design"&gt;API Design&lt;/a&gt; series, where I will review several API design tools and summarize my experiences. There are the following criteria I use in selecting and evaluating the tools:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is free: either open source or a free plan of a paid product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;out-of-the-box functionality is considered only: no plugins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;both web and desktop products are considered&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it allows designing REST API definition in OpenAPI 3.x with JSON/YAML (low-code), UI means (no-code), or a combination of both&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;code generation functionality is not required as there are several 3rd party libraries to do that&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not promoting, just expressing my honest opinion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/api-design-tooling/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (10 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>API Design</category><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/api-design-tooling/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 22:15:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>API Design-First</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/api-design-first/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/api-design-first-back.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article is a part of the &lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/pages/api-design"&gt;API Design&lt;/a&gt; series, where I will uncover API design concepts for my non-technical peers. You don't need to be a developer or an architect to participate to design or even build an API, but there is something you should learn to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we start with API design-first, which takes the opportunity to democratize the API development process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/api-design-first/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (7 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>API Design</category><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/api-design-first/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2022 22:35:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Thoughts about J. Gharajedaghi’s “System Thinking”</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/reading-gharajedaghi-system-thinking/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/gharajedaghi.jpg" width="50%" height="50%" alt="Book Cover" style="display: block; margin:auto"&gt;&lt;br&gt;
This is a new rubric in my blog as I tried to avoid any posts about specific books before. I am taking some notes about the best books I have read. But those are not for the public eye. So this piece was not originally planned to be published. I just feel a need to share something with the world after I read a book in the title. Because that was a wonderful but pretty tough experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we begin, let’s make clear that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is not a review. I will not write about bad books in my blog. By default, any book which has a separate essay is worth reading. Period.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That will be in the form of an internal dialog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OK. What is the full title of this book?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“System Thinking: Managing Chaos and Complexity: A Platform for Designing Business Architecture” by Jamshid Gharajedaghi, 3rd edition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nice. How did you learn about this book?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago when I was listening to a &lt;a href="https://zamesin.ru/ru-podcast-bayram-annakov"&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt; with a guest talking about System Thinking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/reading-gharajedaghi-system-thinking/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Books</category><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/reading-gharajedaghi-system-thinking/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 12:45:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How I overcame my obsession with performance metrics and became a real PO</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/performance-metrics-obsession/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/Meditation-Man-Working.jpg" width="90%" alt="Overcoming the obsession" style="vertical-align:middle;margin:1% 1%"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fell into a common trap of every manager: obsession with performance metrics. Since I have been promoted to the PO role my responsibilities include tracking stats related to the backlog and team performance. That includes the team’s capacity, estimates, velocity, and other specific metrics. In an ideal world, the estimation of planned features matches capacity, the team performs a predicted velocity and (more importantly) delivers features in time. But we all know that doesn’t work this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the story of how I became obsessed with numbers instead of being obsessed with a product. And how I overcame that and shifted my focus to real value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/performance-metrics-obsession/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (6 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/performance-metrics-obsession/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2022 09:48:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sidekick product</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/sidekick-product/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/sidekick.jpg" width="90%" alt="Sidekick with Parent" style="vertical-align:middle;margin:1% 1%"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my career, I participated in the development of a few supplements for so-called “parent” products. They were standalone services with their own, not big, but still considerable business value. Recently I realized that even though those supplement products were developed in different organizations and in different business areas they did have common traits. Moreover, they shared the same problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was something laying on the surface. Sometimes you shoot yourself in the foot twice before starting to see obvious things. What is the nature of those Sidekick products and do they inherit the problems of “bigger brothers”? Let us sort it out in this essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/sidekick-product/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/sidekick-product/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 19:26:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Product Manager: Year One</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/product-manager-year-one/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/pm_year_one.jpg" width="90%" alt="Baby PM" style="vertical-align:middle;margin:1% 1%"&gt;&lt;br&gt;
One year already passed since I have been promoted to a Product Manager position: first 6 months as an Associate (a Junior grade) and then I stepped in as a fully-fledged Product Manager. And that was a drastic shift that made me revisit some aspects of my work and added a new dimension to my view on product development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this essay, I want to summarize my experience with the insights I collected throughout the year. Some of them might be obvious to a more experienced audience. But for me, some of them were kind of revelations, and some of them were hugely underestimated initially. Anyway, it is a good exercise to conduct such a personal retrospective, and the others, I think, can benefit from that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/product-manager-year-one/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/product-manager-year-one/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 07:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tips for Junior BA before going to interview</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/tips-for-junior-ba-interview/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/ba_interview.jpg" width="90%" alt="Interview process" style="vertical-align:middle;margin:1% 1%"&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Recently I was looking for a Junior Business Analyst to join my team. I considered candidates with little or no experience in IT. And that appeared to be a great experience for me. For the first time in my career I:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fully owned job requirements for the position&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;made a final decision to hire someone or not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;was not doing tech part of an interview&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;interviewed Junior-level specialists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not the same as interviewing a Middle or Senior BA. There is a wide variety of topics you can discuss with more experienced professionals: practical cases, challenges, techniques, recent articles, etc. But that is hardly applicable for the Juniors as they can share only their background, knowledge of theory with the ability to apply that in practice. At the very least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/tips-for-junior-ba-interview/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/tips-for-junior-ba-interview/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 18:05:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>“Backward awkwardability” or how to break compatibility and stop worrying</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/backward-compatibility/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/breaking_changes.jpeg" width="90%" alt="Breaking changes everywhere" style="vertical-align:middle;margin:1% 1%"&gt;&lt;br&gt;
When you are responsible for services widely used by other teams inside and partners outside, you most likely become paranoid about maintaining backward compatibility of your API as much as possible. I had no idea about what backward compatibility means in terms of software engineering until I started working on microservices. Those microservices were important for the organization’s success. And in the same time that was a highly volatile environment with rapidly growing functionality and direction changes on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then, I invented the term “backward awkwardability”: when you feel awkward while telling your customers that an upcoming release is not compatible with a previous so they have some work to do. They say something like: “C’mon guys, you introduced breaking changes just a few iterations before! What’s going on?” Ugh, each time I feel sick just remembering those situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we are going to talk about the nature of backward compatibility and how to deal with the breaking changes in terms of API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/backward-compatibility/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (6 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/backward-compatibility/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 13:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Definition of API requirements</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/definition-of-api-requirements/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/api.jpg" width="90%" alt="API" style="vertical-align:middle;margin:1% 1%"&gt;&lt;br&gt;
At some point in my career, I faced a need to specify requirements for API. Those were not typical solution requirements I worked on before. I learned about the API layer which is very common among the enterprise systems. It can hide a set of microservices or a legacy system from the outer world. Like any other system, it is also impacted by stakeholders' needs. And those needs have to be translated into requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are going to decompose the definition of API requirements and see what lies within. I will pay your attention to what should be taken into consideration for the API layer. It is an introduction to this topic as there are other sides of it to explore further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/definition-of-api-requirements/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (10 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/definition-of-api-requirements/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>