<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>IZAKHARAU.ME (Posts about Product Management)</title><link>https://izakharau.me/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://izakharau.me/categories/cat_product-management.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:ilya.zakharau@gmail.com"&gt;Ilya Zakharau&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License BY-NC-SA"
style="border-width:0; margin-bottom:12px;"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2022 10:37:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>How I overcame my obsession with performance metrics and became a real PO</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/performance-metrics-obsession/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/Meditation-Man-Working.jpg" width="90%" alt="Overcoming the obsession" style="vertical-align:middle;margin:1% 1%"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fell into a common trap of every manager: obsession with performance metrics. Since I have been promoted to the PO role my responsibilities include tracking stats related to the backlog and team performance. That includes the team’s capacity, estimates, velocity, and other specific metrics. In an ideal world, the estimation of planned features matches capacity, the team performs a predicted velocity and (more importantly) delivers features in time. But we all know that doesn’t work this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the story of how I became obsessed with numbers instead of being obsessed with a product. And how I overcame that and shifted my focus to real value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/performance-metrics-obsession/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (6 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/performance-metrics-obsession/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2022 09:48:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sidekick product</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/sidekick-product/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/sidekick.jpg" width="90%" alt="Sidekick with Parent" style="vertical-align:middle;margin:1% 1%"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my career, I participated in the development of a few supplements for so-called “parent” products. They were standalone services with their own, not big, but still considerable business value. Recently I realized that even though those supplement products were developed in different organizations and in different business areas they did have common traits. Moreover, they shared the same problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was something laying on the surface. Sometimes you shoot yourself in the foot twice before starting to see obvious things. What is the nature of those Sidekick products and do they inherit the problems of “bigger brothers”? Let us sort it out in this essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/sidekick-product/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/sidekick-product/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 19:26:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Product Manager: Year One</title><link>https://izakharau.me/posts/product-manager-year-one/</link><dc:creator>Ilya Zakharau</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://izakharau.me/images/pm_year_one.jpg" width="90%" alt="Baby PM" style="vertical-align:middle;margin:1% 1%"&gt;&lt;br&gt;
One year already passed since I have been promoted to a Product Manager position: first 6 months as an Associate (a Junior grade) and then I stepped in as a fully-fledged Product Manager. And that was a drastic shift that made me revisit some aspects of my work and added a new dimension to my view on product development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this essay, I want to summarize my experience with the insights I collected throughout the year. Some of them might be obvious to a more experienced audience. But for me, some of them were kind of revelations, and some of them were hugely underestimated initially. Anyway, it is a good exercise to conduct such a personal retrospective, and the others, I think, can benefit from that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://izakharau.me/posts/product-manager-year-one/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://izakharau.me/posts/product-manager-year-one/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 07:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>